Guide to the George Antheil Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
George Antheil Papers,
1919-1959.
Antheil, George, 1900-1959.
3.92 linear feet (4 document boxes, 2 custom made boxes, 1 oversized folder).
Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library Butler Library, New York, NY 10027.
MS#0037
4078528
The George Antheil Papers are composed primarily of correspondence, both professional and personal.
Biographical Note
George Antheil was born on July 8, 1900 in Trenton, New Jersey. His parents were Henry William and Wilhelmine Huse Antheil. Although Antheil claimed to be of Polish descent, he was actually German and grew up speaking both German and English. He attended Trenton Central High School, but there is no indication that he graduated. Antheil studied piano lessons at an early age and in 1919 began to study with Constantin Ivanovich Edler von Sternberg at the Sternberg School of Music. He also briefly studied piano at the Settlement Music School. In his autobiography, Bad Boy of Music, Antheil claimed to have been a student alternately at the Curtis Institute of Music and what he refers to as the "Curtis Settlement School," which did not exist. Both of these statements were untrue.
Antheil traveled around Europe as a concert pianist playing "modern music" as well as his own compositions. Antheil became friends with many of the important intellectuals of that time, including Ernest Hemingway, James Joyce, and Ezra Pound. During this time, and for quite a few years after, Antheil was financially subsidized by Mary Louise Curtis Bok (who founded the Curtis Institute of Music). While in Europe, Antheil met a student named Böski Marcus from Hungary. They married in 1925. Antheil's best known piece during the 1920s was a composition entitled Ballet Mécanique scored for piano and percussion. The American premiere of this piece was deemed a failure and Antheil's reputation was never the same.
In the 1930s, Antheil moved to California and concentrated on writing film scores for such directors as Man Ray and Cecil B. DeMille. He continued to compose symphonies during this time. His 1953 opera, Volpone, opened to mixed reviews, but Antheil continued to write.
In addition to composing, George Antheil was interested in writing in general. He was a music critic, contributed columns to Esqure and other periodicals, and wrote two detective novels based on his hobby of studying glandular endocrinology. His autobiography, Bad Boy of Music, was a bestseller. Antheil is also credited to co-inventing (with Hedy Lamarr) a torpedo guidance system.
George Antheil died of a heart attack in 1959.
Scope and Content
The George Antheil Papers consists primarily of correspondence with a small amount of documents including music scores. Formerly cataloged individuals are listed below. Please note that there is not necessarily correspondence from or to the listed individuals. In some cases, there is only a signature.
Adrian, Gilbert; Antheil, George; Balanchine, George; Bates, Peggy; Bing, Sir Rudolf; Bloach, Ernest; Boulanger, Nadia; Bowles, Paul; Brandt, Carl; Britten, Benjamin; Bullitt, William C.; Buñel, Luis; Cage, John; Calder, Alexander; Cocteau, Jean; Copland, Aaron; Cowell, Henry; Cravath, Paul D.; Dali, Salvador; Dallapiccola, Luigi; Davies, Joseph; DeMille, Cecil B.; Dorati, Antal; Erskine, John; Ferrer, José; Fiedler, Arthur; Germain, André; Gershwin, George; Goldovsky, Boris; Golschmann, Vladimir; Goossens, Eugene; Grainger, Percy A.; Hanson, Howard; Heap, Jane; Hecht, Ben; Hemingway, Ernest; Hindemith, Paul; Hoover, J. Edgar; Hopper, Hedda; Hotchner, Aaron Edward; Huebsch, Ben W.; Hutcheson, Ernest; Jeritza, Maria; Joyce, James; Kahn, Otto; Kierstein, Lincoln; Knight, Eric M.; Kostelanetz, Andre; Koussevitzky, Serge; Kramer, Stanley; Krenek, Ernest; Lambert, Constant; Léger, Fernand; Leinsdorf, Erich; Lenya, Lotte; Léon, Paul; Lewis, Wyndham; Lieberson, Goddard; Lin, Yutang; Luening, Otto; MacLeish, Archibald; Malko, Nicolai; Michonze; Milhaud, Darius; Miró, Joan; Monotti, Francesco; Mitropoulos, Dimitri; Monteux, Pierre; Moore, Douglas; Norris, Charles G.; Ormandy, Eugene; O'Sullivan, John; Picasso, Pablo; Post, Marjorie Merriweather; Putnam, George P.; Reed, Ruth; Reiner, Fritz; Reiter, Max; Rhee, Syngman; Riegger, Wallingford; Schnitzler, Arthur; Selznick, David O.; Sessions, Roger; Sternberg, Constantin von; Stoessel, Albert F.; Stokowski, Leopold; Stravinski, Igor; Szell, George; Tanner, Allen; Taylor, Deems; Thompson, Randall; Van Vechter, Carl; Wallenstein, Alfred F.; Weaver, Harriet Shaw; Weill, Kurt; Winchell, Walter
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in two series.
Series I: Correspondence, 1919-1959
Series II: Subject Files, 1919-1955
Subjects
Antheil, George, 1900-1959.; Heinsheimer, Hans, 1900-1993.; Sternberg, Constantin von, 1852-1924.; Stoessel, Albert, 1894-1943.; Stokowski, Leopold, 1882-1977.; Zimbalis, Mary Louise Curtis Bok, 1876-1970.; Avant-garde (Aesthetics)--France--Paris.; Composers--United States--Correspondence.; Endocrinology.; Motion picture music.; Music.; Music--France--Paris--20th century.; Orchestral music.; Pianists--United States.; Correspondence.; Scores.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located on-site.
Donation by Peter Antheil, 1984.
Purchase from Peter Antheil, 1990.
Gift of Mrs. Mira Gerstmann, 1989.
- Series I: Correspondence, 1919-1959
  Series I contains letters exchanged between George Antheil and his colleagues. Many of the correspondents are conductors, music directors, and other individuals involved in the music business. There are also letters from some of George's companions during his time in Europe, such as Ernest Hemingway, James Joyce, and Kurt Weill. The correspondence with Constantin von Sternberg illustrates Sternberg's admiration for Antheil as a young musician while the letters with Mary Louise Curtis Bok Zimbalist illustrate Antheil's financial strain and his need for recognition. Several of the letters are from or to his wife, Böske.
  - A, 1930-1931, 1949-1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Antheil Family, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Baker through Boddy, 1920-1926, 1934-1956 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bomhard through Butts, 1933-1956 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - C, 1929-1955 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - D, 1937-1956 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Dyne, Michael, 1954-1957 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - E, 1929, 1939-1955 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - F, 1945-1957 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - G, 1930-1957 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Golschmann, Vladimir, 1937-1959 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - H, 1932-1958 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Heinsheimer, Hans, 1928-1931, 1942-1957, (2 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 3 to 4)
  - J, 1930-1941, 1952-1955 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - K, 1932-1957 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - L, 1940-1956 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Levine, Joseph and Mary, 1952-1959 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Levy, Edwin, 1954-1957 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Lewis, E. Henry, 1955-1957 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - M, 1931-1959 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Mills, Ted, 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - N, 1946-1955 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - O, 1930, 1945-1949 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - P, 1938-1955 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Perry, Elaine and Alfred, 1953-1955 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - R, 1925-1957 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Sabatini through Siegel, 1923-1958 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Signal through Szell, 1923-1958 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Sternberg, Constantin Ivanovich Edler von, 1919-1921 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Stokowski, Leopold, 1926-1932, 1943-1949 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - T, 1930-1956 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - U through V, 1928-1930, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - W through Z, 1930, 1941-1957 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Weintraub, Eugene, 1951-1956 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Zimbalist, Mary Louise Curtis Bok, 1933-1945, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Unidentified Correspondence, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Series II: Subject Files, 1919-1955
  This small series holds articles, printed material, such as a music program, and several scores. Of interest are the documents relating to Antheil's piece Railroad Theme in which he claims that his work has been plagiarized.
  - About George Antheil, 1940, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Printed Material, 1926-1932, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Scores
    - Railroad Theme, 1939 (Mapcase 14-P-2)
      (with notes)
    - Sonata Number One, 1919 (Box 5)
    - Symphony Number Four, 1942 (Box 6)